{
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Propositional_Logic — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Propositional_Logic — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following options is CORRECT given three positive integers x, y\nand z, and a predicate <br> \\(P(x)=\\neg (x=1)\\wedge \\forall y(\\exists z(x=y*z))\\Rightarrow (y=x)\\vee (y=1)\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P(x) being true means that x is a prime number</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P(x) being true means that x is a number other than 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P(x) is always true irrespective of the value of x</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P(x) being true means that x has exactly two factors other than 1 and x</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>P(x) being true means that x is a prime number</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2132/gate2011-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Suppose the predicate F(x,y,t) is used to represent the statement that person x\ncan fool person y at time t. which one of the statements below expresses best\nthe meaning of the formula \\(\\forall x \\exists y \\exists t(\\neg F (x, y, t))\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Everyone can fool some person at some time</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>No one can fool everyone all the time</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Everyone cannot fool some person all the time</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>No one can fool some person at some time</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>No one can fool everyone all the time</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1156/gate2010-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following well-formed formulae:<br> I. \\(\\neg \\forall x(P(x))\\) <br> II. \\(\\neg \\exists x(P(x))\\) <br>  III. \\(\\neg \\exists x(\\neg P(x))\\)  <br> IV. \\(\\exists x(\\neg P(x))\\)<br> Which of the above are equivalent? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and III</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and IV</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II and IV</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and IV</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/803/gate2009-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is the most appropriate logical formula to represent\nthe statement? <br><br>\"Gold and silver ornaments are precious\".\n<br><br> The following notations are used: <br><br>\nG(x): x is a gold ornament<br>\nS(x): x is a silver ornament<br>\nP(x): x is precious <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x(P(x)\\rightarrow (G(x)\\wedge S(x)))\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x((G(x) \\wedge S(x)) \\rightarrow P(x))\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x((G(x) \\wedge S(x)) \\rightarrow P(x))\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x((G(x) \\vee S(x)) \\rightarrow P(x))\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x((G(x) \\vee S(x)) \\rightarrow P(x))\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/800/gate2009-23#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is the negation of \\([\\forall x, \\alpha \\rightarrow(\\exists y, \\beta \\rightarrow(\\forall u, \\exists v, y))]\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\({[\\exists x, \\alpha \\rightarrow(\\forall y, \\beta \\rightarrow(\\exists u, \\forall v, y))]}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\({[\\exists x, \\alpha \\rightarrow(\\forall y, \\beta \\rightarrow(\\exists u, \\forall v, \\neg y))]}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\({[\\forall x, \\neg \\alpha \\rightarrow(\\exists y, \\neg \\beta \\rightarrow(\\forall u, \\exists v, \\neg y))]}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\({[\\exists x, \\alpha \\wedge(\\forall y, \\beta \\wedge(\\exists u, \\forall v, \\neg y))]}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\({[\\exists x, \\alpha \\wedge(\\forall y, \\beta \\wedge(\\exists u, \\forall v, \\neg y))]}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3283/gate2008-it-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following first order formulae is logically valid? <br>Here \\(\\alpha(x)\\) is a first order formula with x as a free variable, and \\(\\beta\\) is a first order formula with no free variable.<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\([\\beta \\rightarrow (\\exists x, \\alpha(x))] \\rightarrow [\\forall x, \\beta \\rightarrow \\alpha(x)]\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\([\\exists x, \\beta \\rightarrow \\alpha(x)] \\rightarrow [\\beta \\rightarrow (\\forall x, \\alpha(x))]\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\([(\\exists x, \\alpha(x)) \\rightarrow \\beta] \\rightarrow [\\forall x, \\alpha(x) \\rightarrow \\beta]\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\([(\\forall x, \\alpha(x)) \\rightarrow \\beta] \\rightarrow [\\forall x, \\alpha(x) \\rightarrow \\beta]\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\([(\\exists x, \\alpha(x)) \\rightarrow \\beta] \\rightarrow [\\forall x, \\alpha(x) \\rightarrow \\beta]\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3282/gate2008-it-21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>P and Q are two propositions. Which of the following logical expressions are\nequivalent?<br>  I. \\(P\\vee \\sim Q \\)<br> II.\\(\\sim (\\sim  P \\wedge Q) \\)<br> III.\\((P \\wedge Q)\\vee (P\\wedge \\sim Q)\\vee (\\sim P\\wedge \\sim Q) \\)<br> IV. \\((P\\wedge Q)\\vee \\vee (P\\wedge \\sim Q)\\vee (\\sim P\\wedge Q)\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only I and II</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only I, II and III</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only I, II and IV</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All of I, II III and IV</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Only I, II and III</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/442/gate2008-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let fsa and pda be two predicates such that fsa(x) means x is a finite state\nautomaton, and pda(y) means that y is a pushdown automaton. Let equivalent\nbe another predicate such that equivalent (a, b) means a and b are equivalent.\nWhich of the following first order logic statements represents the following:<br>\nEach finite state automaton has an equivalent pushdown automaton <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((\\forall x \\; fsa(x))\\Rightarrow (\\exists y \\;  pda(y)\\wedge equivalent (x,y))\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(~ \\forall y(\\exists x \\; fsa(x) \\Rightarrow pda(y)\\wedge equivalent(x,y))\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x\\; \\exists y(fsa(x)\\wedge pda(y)\\wedge equivalent(x,y))\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x \\;  \\exists y(fsa(y)\\wedge pda(x)\\wedge equivalent(x,y))\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((\\forall x \\; fsa(x))\\Rightarrow (\\exists y \\;  pda(y)\\wedge equivalent (x,y))\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "None of these.<br><a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/441/gate2008-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Identify the correct translation into logical notation of the following assertion.<br>\nSome boys in the class are taller than all the girls<br>\nNote: taller (x, y) is true if x is taller than y. <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((\\exists x) (\\text{boy}(x) \\rightarrow (\\forall y) (\\text{girl}(y) \\land \\text{taller}(x, y)))\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((\\exists x) (\\text{boy}(x) \\land (\\forall y) (\\text{girl}(y) \\land \\text{taller}(x, y)))\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((\\exists x) (\\text{boy}(x) \\rightarrow (\\forall y) (\\text{girl}(y) \\rightarrow \\text{taller}(x, y)))\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((\\exists x) (\\text{boy}(x) \\land (\\forall y) (\\text{girl}(y) \\rightarrow \\text{taller}(x, y)))\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((\\exists x) (\\text{boy}(x) \\land (\\forall y) (\\text{girl}(y) \\rightarrow \\text{taller}(x, y)))\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1020/gate2004-23-isro2007-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Which one of these first-order logic formulae is valid? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x\\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\implies Q\\left(x\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\forall xP\\left(x\\right)\\implies \\forall xQ\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\exists x\\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\vee Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\implies \\left(\\exists xP\\left(x\\right)\\implies \\exists xQ\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\exists x\\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\wedge Q\\left(x\\right)\\right) \\iff \\left(\\exists xP\\left(x\\right) \\wedge \\exists xQ\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x \\exists y P\\left(x, y\\right)\\implies \\exists y \\forall x P\\left(x, y\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x\\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\implies Q\\left(x\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\forall xP\\left(x\\right)\\implies \\forall xQ\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3454/gate2007-it-21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Let Graph(x) be a predicate which denotes that x is a graph. Let Connected(x) be\na predicate which denotes that x is connected. Which of the following first order\nlogic sentences DOES NOT represent the statement: \"Not every graph is connected\"? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\neg \\forall x (Graph(x)\\Rightarrow Connected(x))\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\exists  x(Graph(x) \\Rightarrow \\neg Connected(x))\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\neg \\forall  x(\\neg Graph(x) \\vee Connected(x))\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x(Graph(x) \\Rightarrow \\neg Connected(x))\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x(Graph(x) \\Rightarrow \\neg Connected(x))\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1220/gate2007-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following first order logic formula in which R is a binary relation symbol.<br>\n\\(\\forall x \\forall y(R(x, y) \\Longrightarrow R(y, x))\\),<br>The formula is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>satisfiable and valid</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>satisfiable and so is its negation</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>unsatisfiable but its negation is valid</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>satisfiable but its negation is unsatisfiable</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>satisfiable and so is its negation</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3560/gate2006-it-21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following propositional statements: <br> \\(P1:((A\\wedge B)\\rightarrow C)\\equiv (A\\rightarrow C)\\wedge (B\\rightarrow C)\\) <br> \\( P2:((A\\vee B)\\rightarrow C)\\equiv (A\\rightarrow C)\\vee (B\\rightarrow C) \\)<br> Which one of the following is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P1 is a tautology, but not P2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P2 is a tautology, but not P1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P1 and P2 are both tautologies</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Both P1 and P2 are not tautologies</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Both P1 and P2 are not tautologies</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/990/gate2006-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the first order predicate calculus statements given below correctly\nexpresses the following English statement? <br><br>Tigers and lions attack if they are hungry or threatened. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x \\) \\([(tiger(x)\\wedge lion(x))\\rightarrow \\) \\(\\{(hungry(x)\\vee theatened(x))\\rightarrow attacks(x)\\}]\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x \\) \\([(tiger(x)\\vee lion(x))\\rightarrow \\) \\(\\{(hungry(x)\\vee theatened(x))\\wedge attacks(x)\\}]\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x\\) \\([(tiger(x)\\vee lion(x))\\rightarrow \\) \\( \\{attacks (x)\\rightarrow (hungry(x)\\wedge theatened(x))\\}]\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x \\) \\([(tiger(x)\\vee lion(x))\\rightarrow \\) \\( \\{(hungry(x)\\vee theatened(x))\\rightarrow attacks(x)\\}]\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\forall x \\) \\([(tiger(x)\\vee lion(x))\\rightarrow \\) \\( \\{(hungry(x)\\vee theatened(x))\\rightarrow attacks(x)\\}]\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/989/gate2006-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let P(x) and Q(x) be arbitrary predicates. Which of the following statements is always TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\left(\\forall x \\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\vee Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\left(\\forall x P\\left(x\\right)\\right) \\vee \\left(\\forall xQ\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\forall x \\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\implies Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\left(\\forall x P\\left(x\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\forall xQ\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\forall x\\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\right) \\implies \\forall x \\left( Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\forall x \\left( P\\left(x\\right) \\implies Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\forall x \\left( P\\left(x\\right)\\right) \\Leftrightarrow \\left(\\forall x \\left( Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right) \\right) \\implies \\left(\\forall x \\left (P\\left(x\\right) \\Leftrightarrow Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\forall x \\left(P\\left(x\\right) \\implies Q\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\left(\\forall x P\\left(x\\right)\\right) \\implies \\left(\\forall xQ\\left(x\\right)\\right)\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3783/gate2005-it-36\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}